<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Almighty his gracious token of love to his friend Abraham, or, A sermon preached in the Cathedral Church of Bristol, January 3, 1674 by Rich. Towgood ...</title>
            <author>Towgood, Richard, 1595?-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13292509</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13292509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98854</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63011)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98854)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 440:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Almighty his gracious token of love to his friend Abraham, or, A sermon preached in the Cathedral Church of Bristol, January 3, 1674 by Rich. Towgood ...</title>
                  <author>Towgood, Richard, 1595?-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 26, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.C. for H. Brome ... and are to be sold by Humfrey Dixon ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts VII, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>God --  Love --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98854:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98854:1"/>
            <p>THE ALMIGHTY <hi>His Gracious Token of Love</hi> TO HIS Friend Abraham.</p>
            <p>OR A SERMON Preached in the Cathedral Church of <hi>BRISTOL, January</hi> 3. 1674.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> RICH. TOWGOOD, B.D. <hi>now Dean of</hi> Briſtol, <hi>and when time was, Chaplain in Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to His late Sacred Majeſty King</hi> CHARLES <hi>the Firſt, of moſt bleſſed and moſt renowned memory.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>In Chriſt Jeſus neither circumciſion availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but a new creature,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 6.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>H.C.</hi> for <hi>H. Brome,</hi> at the Gun at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Panls,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Humfrey Dixon,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet, Briſtol.</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98854:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98854:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God GUIDO, by Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence Lord Biſhop of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reverend Father in God, and my much honoured Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Deſire I dare not deny, it is unto me inſtead of a Command; but I fear whatſoever it was that your Lordſhip approved of at the hearing, will not ſeem ſo approvable at the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Horace</hi> his Verſe I may crave leave a little to change, and ſay,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Soepius inſtibant animum dimiſſa per aurem,</l>
               <l>Quam quae ſunt oculis ſubjecta fidelibus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That which may paſs current out of a popular Pulpit, may not perhaps reliſh ſo well out of a publick Preſs. However, that which may ſerve to edifie a hundred, may ſerve alſo to edifie a thouſand. And the world, I hope, may hereby ſee, that our ordinary labours in <hi>Briſtol</hi> (which intend to ſound no further than the walls
<pb facs="tcp:98854:3"/>of the Church, in which they are deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) are not ſo extremely contemptible, that our Hearers had need to keep up to themſelves a company of Schiſmatical Teachers, fetch'd from far, to ſupply our defects. For I dare aſſure your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, there are many Sermons frequently preached by my Brethren in <hi>Briſtol</hi> which may challenge the light rather than this now preſented to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and yet I reckon this may paſs without offence, having received the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of your Lordſhips judicious ear; and that it hath made bold to prefix before it your <hi>Reverend Name.</hi> I humbly beg, and hope, you will be pleaſed, as being the occaſion of it your ſelf, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably to vouchſafe a pardon to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt obliged and moſt humble Servant.</hi> Rich. Towgood.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98854:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED In the Cathedral Church of <hi>BRISTOL, Januar.</hi> 3. 1674/5.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACT. vij. 8. former part.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And he gave him the Covenant of Circumciſion.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE words are part of a Sermon preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by St. <hi>Stephen</hi> the <hi>Protomartyr,</hi> before the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> or Council at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> not long after our Saviours Aſcenſion. What St. <hi>Stephens</hi> ſcope is in this Sermon, contained in this Chapter, or what he aims at in this particular paſſage, I ſhall not now ſtand to inquire. I ſhall at preſent look upon the Words as bearing full and perfect ſence in themſelves without any reference to the occaſion or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence, further then doth concern the two Relatives or Perſons here ſpoken of, <hi>He</hi> and <hi>Him.</hi> Only that ye may not ſtumble at the choice of this Text concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an antiquated Ceremony, ye may be pleaſed to conſider that according to the order appointed by the Church, the anniverſary Commemoration of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours <hi>Circumciſion</hi> is not quite over; as doth appear by the Epiſtle, Goſpel, and Collect for this preſent Day, and therefore a Text concerning <hi>Circumciſion</hi> is not unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable. Beſides, from this time we reckon the beginning of the <hi>New year,</hi> and Circumciſion was a ſign of a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98854:4"/>
               <hi>New-heart,</hi> and of <hi>newneſs</hi> of Life. And laſtly, the beginning of this moneth is the time wherein friends of the chief account do uſually gratifie one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with gifts of kindneſs, and tokens of love; And here the Text tells us of a ſpecial Gift that the Almighty God vouchſafed unto <hi>Abraham</hi> his friend, for theſe two are the <hi>He</hi> and the <hi>Him</hi> here ſpoken of, as is plain by the Verſes foregoing: <hi>He</hi> gave <hi>Him,</hi> that is, God gave <hi>Abraham</hi> the Covenant of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion; ſo that though I cannot ſay, here is a <hi>New-years</hi> Gift, yet here is no ſmall token of Gods love to <hi>Abraham.</hi> And concerning this Token of Love (to come now to the Words themſelves) we have four things obſervable in the Text.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What it was.</item>
               <item>2. Of what worth it was.</item>
               <item>3. Who gave it.</item>
               <item>4. To whom it was given.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Of theſe by Gods gracious aſsiſtance and your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian patience in their order; and firſt of the firſt, what it was. It was the Ordinance of Circumciſion. God commanded <hi>Abraham</hi> this ſervice; and what kind of ſervice this was, and by whom to be obſerved, and at what time to be performed is fully declared by the Holy Ghoſt himſelf, and cannot better be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed than in his own Words, as we find them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. from the tenth to the twelfth: <hi>This is my Covenant</hi> (ſaith the Lord to <hi>Abraham</hi>) <hi>which ye ſhall keep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and you, and thy ſeed after thee; every manchild among you ſhall be circumciſed; And ye ſhall circumciſe the fleſh of your foreskin, and it ſhall be a token of the Covenant between me and you; And he that is eight days old ſhall be circumciſed among you, every manchild in your generations, he that is born
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98854:4"/>in the houſe, or bought with mony of any ſtranger which is not of thy ſeed.</hi> This was the ſervice that God commanded him and all his poſterity. And a hard ſervice it was, as appeared in that when the <hi>Sechemites</hi> were by deceit perſwaded by the ſons of <hi>Jacob</hi> to be circumciſed, their whole City by reaſon of their ſoreneſs after they were circumciſed, was not able to defend themſelves againſt two men; <hi>For it came to paſs on the third day when they were ſore, that two of the ſons of</hi> Jacob, Symeon <hi>and</hi> Levi, Dinahs <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, took each man his ſword, and came upon the City boldly, and ſlew all the Males,</hi> Gen. 34.25. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is ſaid of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they were all circumciſed at their entrance into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> becauſe they had not been circumciſed by the way, <hi>That they abode in their places in the Camp till they were whole,</hi> Joſh. 5.7, 8. But yet more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth the hardſhip of this ſervice appear by that of <hi>Zipporah,</hi> who when ſhe was enforced to circumciſe her Son, ſaid thus unto <hi>Moſes</hi> her Husband not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bitterneſs, <hi>A bloody husband art thou to me;</hi> and doubled it, <hi>A bloody husband, becauſe of the circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> Exod. 4.25, 26. A hard ſervice it was, and yet to be laid upon their Infants when they were but eight days old: Surely, we may juſtly take up the words of the Apoſtle, which were uttered by him in another caſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.40. <hi>God hath provided ſome better thing for us.</hi> Inſtead of that hard ſervice (for abrogated now it is, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2.) God hath appointed unto us the Sacrament of Baptiſm, which as for the uſe is more perſpicuous, ſo for the quality is far leſs painful; and yet ſee the fond tenderneſs of Parents, and the fooliſh niceneſs of people now-a-days is ſuch, that they can ſcarce ſuffer a little cold water to be ſprinkled on their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98854:5"/>Children; nay a few drops more than ordinary, ſhall procure as bitter words againſt their Miniſter, as <hi>Zip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porah</hi>'s were againſt her Husband.</p>
            <p>But (to paſs by this) here we may take notice, that St. <hi>Stephen</hi> doth call this Ordinance the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Circumciſion,</hi> and ſo it is alſo called in that place forementioned, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. The Lord there thus ſpeaking, <hi>This is my</hi> Covenant <hi>which ye ſhall keep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and you, and thy ſeed after thee, every man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child among you ſhall be</hi> circumciſed. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> both there and here is called the <hi>Covenant,</hi> when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and in truth it was but the <hi>Sign</hi> of the Covenant. The Covenant was this, as it is plainly ſet down, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. The Lord there ſaying unto <hi>Abraham, I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee in their generations for an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant, to be a God unto thee and thy ſeed after thee.</hi> This was the <hi>Covenant</hi> on the Lords part, that he would be a God unto <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed; and in the ſame words was included the <hi>Covenant</hi> on <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> part, that <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed ſhould take the Lord to be their God, and ſhould worſhip him, ſerve and obey him as their God. This was the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and of this Covenant, Circumciſion was inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted to be the <hi>Sign,</hi> and ſo it is plainly declared, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. <hi>Ye ſhall circumciſe the fleſh of your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin, and it ſhall be a</hi> token <hi>of the Covenant between me and you:</hi> and ſo the Apoſtle ſpeaks of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. Saying of <hi>Abraham, He received the</hi> Sign <hi>of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, (i.e.)</hi> He received Circumciſion, which was a <hi>Sign.</hi> It is the uſual language of the Holy Ghoſt in Sacramental ſpeeches to give to the <hi>ſign</hi> the name of the <hi>thing ſignified.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> had two principal Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, but more they had leſs Principals; and the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98854:5"/>truth of this, holds in both ſorts. Their two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal and ordinary Sacraments, were Circumciſion and the Paſchal Lamb. Concerning the former it hath been already ſhewed; yea may ſee it alſo concerning the latter. If ye look into <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.11, ye ſhall find theſe words concerning the Paſchal Lamb, <hi>Thus ye ſhall eat it, with your loins girded, your ſhoes on your feet, and your ſtaff in your hand; and ye ſhall eat it in haſte, it is the Lords Paſsover.</hi> The Paſsover was the Act of the Angel paſſing over the Houſes of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when he ſmote all the firſt-born in the Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and yet the <hi>Lamb,</hi> ye ſee, is called by the name of the <hi>Paſsover.</hi> The like we may ſay of other of their Sacraments: I will inſtance but in one, and that is the <hi>Rock</hi> out of which, when <hi>Moſes</hi> had ſmitten it with his Rod, water came forth for the relief and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Num.</hi> 20.11. And this <hi>Rock,</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, was Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. No man will ſay that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> meant the <hi>Rock</hi> was Chriſt in regard of the ſubſtance, but only by ſignification; and ſo Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> interprets it, <hi>Petra erat Chriſtus, quia ſignificabat Chriſtum, Epiſt.</hi> 102. <hi>ad Euod.</hi> Neither is this kind of Metonymy and Figure uſed only in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Speeches, but in thoſe Speeches alſo where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is no Myſtery of Religion contained; as in the interpretation of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Dream, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in his Dream ſaw ſeven fat-fleſhed Kine come out of the River, and after them ſeven other lean-fleſhed Kine, <hi>Verſe</hi> 2. <hi>Joſeph</hi> in his interpretation thereof doth thus ſpeak unto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Verſe 26, 27. <hi>The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven good Kine are ſeven years, and the ſeven thin Kine are ſeven years.</hi> The meaning is, the ſeven Kine of the one ſort and the other do ſignifie ſeven years; the name of the <hi>thing ſignified</hi> being attributed to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98854:6"/>
               <hi>Sign,</hi> which ye ſee is a uſual kind of ſpeaking both in the Old and New Teſtament. And this may ſtop the mouths of the Papiſts about their Tranſubſtantiation; who becauſe our Saviour at the Inſtitution of the Lords Supper, taking Bread in his Hand, ſaid, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> do therefore think that the ſubſtance of Bread at the Sacrament muſt needs be turned into the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of our Saviours Body: But ſeeing other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Speeches are Figuratively underſtood, Why ſhould we conceive that our Saviours Words are not ſo to be underſtood alſo? A real Preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament we acknowledg, for the Body and Blood of Chriſt, according to our Church-Catechiſm, are verily and indeed, taken and received of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the Lords Supper, verily and indeed, that is, really, yet not carnally, but Sacramentally, not Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, but Spiritually. For otherwiſe, how could Believers eat the Fleſh of Chriſt and drink his Blood before his Fleſh had any <hi>exiſtence</hi> or <hi>being</hi> in the World? The Apoſtle doth tell us that the believing <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs did eat the <hi>ſame ſpiritual meat, and drink the ſame ſpiritual drink</hi> that we do, and that is none other but the Body and Blood of Chriſt, and yet Chriſt was not then incarnate, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3, 4. Their <hi>Manna</hi> was the Body of Chriſt, and their <hi>water out of the Rock</hi> was the Blood of Chriſt; not in ſubſtance but in ſignification, they did ſignifie the Body and Blood of Chriſt. And ſurely, in all reaſon thoſe Propoſitions and Sentences of Scripture that are incongruous to reaſon when they are taken in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſence, but ſuitable to reaſon in a figurative ſence; in all reaſon I ſay, they ought to be taken Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratively. And this the Holy Ghoſt himſelf doth teach us. For when Saint <hi>John</hi> had ſeen ſeven Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98854:6"/>Candleſticks, <hi>And in the midſt of the ſeven Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks, one like unto the Son of Man,</hi> Rev. 1 12, 13. who had alſo <hi>in his right hand ſeven Stars,</hi> verſ. 16. the Lord himſelf doth expound the meaning thereof, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. in theſe words: <hi>The myſtery of the ſeven ſtars which thou ſaweſt in my right hand, and the ſeven golden Candleſticks. The ſeven ſtars, are the Angels</hi> (that is, the Biſhops) <hi>of the ſeven Churches, and the ſeven Candleſticks which thou ſaweſt, are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches.</hi> So in theſe two Propoſitions, The ſeven Stars are the Angels of the ſeven Churches, and the ſeven Candleſticks are the ſeven Churches, the Lord ſaith there is a <hi>myſtery,</hi> that is, they are not literally, but miſtically, or figuratively to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. Multitude of ſuch ſpeeches we find in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which cannot poſſibly be otherwiſe underſtood; as when <hi>Joſeph</hi> interpreted <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler, and his Bakers Dreams: The <hi>three branches,</hi> ſaith he, are <hi>three days,</hi> Gen. 40.12. And again, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>The three Baskets, are three days,</hi> that is, they ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie three days. So, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.7. <hi>The vineyard of the Lord of Hoſts is the Houſe of a Iſrel,</hi> that is, doth ſignifie the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> So likewiſe, <hi>Theſe bones are the whole Houſe of Iſrael,</hi> that is, they ſignifie the houſe of <hi>Iſrael, Ezek.</hi> 37.11. Look upon our Saviours parable, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.37. I will mention but a branch or two of it. <hi>The field is the world, the tears are the Children of the wicked ones, the harveſt is the end of the world, and the reapers are the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> that is, they ſignifie theſe things. I'le add but one inſtance more, and that is in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Theſe</hi> (i. e. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> two wives) are <hi>the two Covenants;</hi> the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, they ſignifie the two Covenants. Now when theſe paſſages of Scripture, and many others more, cannot
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98854:7"/>be underſtood but by a Metonymy figuratively, why ſhould our Saviours words, <hi>This is my body,</hi> only be excepted from this general way of interpretation, and have another interpretation aſſixed unto them, which is contrary both to Scripture; and to Senſe, to Reaſon and to the Interpretation of the Ancient Fathers. To Scripture, becauſe the Scripture tells us that Chriſts Body is aſcended up into Heaven, and that the Heavens <hi>muſt</hi> receive him until the times of reſtitution of all things <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the day of Judgment, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.9. and 3.21.</p>
            <p>And if it <hi>muſt</hi> be in Heaven (as the words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. do plainly ſignifie) then he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be here on Earth too; and this argument our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf doth elſewhere make good, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.62. For whereas, when our Saviour preached at <hi>Capernaum</hi> and told them, <hi>except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his blood, ye have no life in you,</hi> ibid. <hi>verſe.</hi> 53. the hearers were offended at it; and ſaid, not only, <hi>how can this man give us his fleſh to eat?</hi> but alſo, <hi>this is an hard ſaying, who can hear it?</hi> Our Saviour to take away this offence, and to give them the true meaning of his words, ſaith thus unto them, <hi>ibid. verſe.</hi> 62. what and <hi>if ye ſhall ſee the Son of man aſcend up where he was before?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, when ye ſhall ſee my Body to be aſcended up into Heaven, then I hope, you will underſtand that I ſpeak not of this carnal eating of my fleſh that ye dream of; for my Body will be then in Heaven, and there <hi>muſt</hi> continue. And this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holds good againſt the carnal eating of Chriſts Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the Sacrament alſo, though our Saviour doth not ſpeak thereof in that place; ſo contrary to Scripture is this interpretation of our Saviours words. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary it is to Senſe; For that which we receive with our hands at the Lords Table, it is not fleſh but bread,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98854:7"/>bread to our ſight, bread to our feeling, and bread to our taſte; contrary to reaſon it is alſo, and that in two reſpects; 1. In that, if the words were literally meant, our Saviour then at the Inſtitution, when he took the bread and uttered the words, had his own body in his hand, and ſo he had there two bodies, one ſitting at the table, and the other in his hand upon the table; and this is not very reaſonable. Secondly, In that, if at the adminiſtration, the fleſh of Chriſt in the very ſubſtance were there, it would ſtand us in no ſtead; for it is <hi>the ſpirit that quickneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing.</hi> Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.63. <hi>My fleſh is meat indeed,</hi> ibid. <hi>ver.</hi> 55. And why then doth our Saviour ſay here, the fleſh profiteth nothing. Our Saviour doth not contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and thereby it is plain, his meaning is, that the carnal <hi>Capernaitical</hi> eating of his fleſh, ſuch as the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernacies</hi> there thought he ſpake of, was of no uſe at all. And laſtly, Contrary it is to the interpretation of the Ancient Fathers I'le mention but two or three very breif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>Turt. lib.</hi> 4. againſt <hi>Marcion,</hi> thus ſpeaks, <hi>Chriſtus acceptum panem &amp; diſtributum diſcipulis, corpus ſuum illum fecit, hoc eſt corpus meum dicendo, i.e. figura corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris mei.</hi> Bread taken and diſtributed to his Diſciples he made his body, by ſaying, This is my body, that is, the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of my body Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to the ſame purpoſe doth uſe the ſame word, <hi>figura. Figura eſt corporis &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis Domini noſtri Jeſu Chriſti. l.</hi> 4. <hi>de ſacramentis, cap.</hi> 5. and Saint <hi>Aug.</hi> on the third <hi>Pſal.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Dominus Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ad hibuit ad convivium, in quo corporis &amp; ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſui figuram diſcipulis commendavit &amp; tradidit.</hi> That is, The Lord entertained <hi>Judas</hi> at the feaſt wherein he commended and gave to his Diſciples the figure of his body and blood. Theſe three, to add no more, do agree in this particular, and they all uſe the ſame word <hi>figura,</hi> whereby they ſignified that the bread is nor turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98854:8"/>to the Body of Chriſt, but was a <hi>ſign</hi> or <hi>figure</hi> of his Body, though called by the name thereof. It is the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Holy Ghoſt to give to the <hi>ſign</hi> the name of the <hi>thing ſignified;</hi> ſo it is here in the Text, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Circumciſion is called the <hi>Covenant,</hi> which was but a <hi>ſign</hi> of the Covenant. He gave him the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Circumciſion. One thing more there is to be obſerved from this title, the Covenant of Circumciſion, which I will touch but briefly; and it is this, That the Almighty God in his Sacraments doth make a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> with his people. Circumciſion was a Sacrament, for there was a ſign and a thing ſignified, as before was ſhewed; and therein God entered into <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed, The Paſsover was a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and thereby there was a <hi>Covenant</hi> made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and his people. The <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> ſent abroad a Proclamation, exhorting the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to come to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to keep the Paſsover, which had ſome years formerly been neglected, he thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks them, <hi>Now be not ſtiff-necked as your Fathers were, but yeild your ſelves unto the Lord;</hi> in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal it is thus expreſſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, give the hand unto the Lord, and ſo it is rendred in the Margent of our Bibles 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 30.8. Now to give the hand, ye know, is a circumſtance and ſign of entring into <hi>Covenant;</hi> and by this expreſſion is intimated, that by keeping the Paſse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, they made a <hi>Covenant</hi> with the Lord. The like is to be <hi>ſaid</hi> of our Sacrament of Baptiſm; for the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. in reſpect of the inward part of it, doth calliit <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that word though it be by divers diverfly rendred, as by our tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, an <hi>anſwer,</hi> by the vulgar Latin, <hi>Interrogatio;</hi> yet it is generally conceived that the Apoſtle doth therein allude unto the queſtions and anſwers that were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98854:8"/>made at the baptizing of people converted to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; Such as, <hi>Doſt thou believe? I do believe,</hi> &amp;c, which had their beginning and uſe even in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, as may be collected from <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. And therefore by ſome, the word is rendred <hi>ſtipulatio,</hi> that is, a <hi>Covenant,</hi> a <hi>Bargain,</hi> or an <hi>Agreement</hi> between two, one asking the queſtion, and the other anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Such a thing is Baptiſm, a <hi>Covenant</hi> between God and us; and though thoſe queſtions and anſwers were omitted, yet this <hi>Covenant</hi> is included and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the very words which by our Saviour are appointed to be uſed at the Sacrament of Baptiſm, that is, <hi>To Baptize in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. Into the Name, or in the Name of the Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Trinity, that is, into the Protection of the Father, into the Redemption of the Son, and into the Sanctification of the Holy Ghoſt. This is the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant on Gods part; and theſe are the Promiſes that are made of God unto us in that Sacrament, whereof our Church-Catechiſm makes mention: And on our part the Covenant is, that we will be his Servants, and yield all obedience to the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. And this Covenant we renew when we come to the Lords Supper; for the Lord doth offer us his Son to be our Saviour, and thither we come to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, that we wholly rely upon him and his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and to yield up our ſelves wholly to him and his ſervice. Take we heed therefore, all of us, that have been baptized, and have received the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, (as for others, they are not in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, nor can expect Protection or Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from him); take we heed, I ſay, that we care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully perform the Covenant. Our Covenant is, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98854:9"/>to yield obedience unto God, and that we cannot do, without renouncing the works of the Devil, and the ſinful luſts of the fleſh: And if we fail on our part, God is not bound on his part. Beſides, he will not take it well at our hands, if we break Covenants with him; he will have a quarrel againſt us for the breach of Covenants; nay, he tells us plainly, he will avenge the quarrel of his Covenant, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.25. Well, ye ſee Circumciſion was called the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; ye ſee that there was a Covenant in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, as there is alſo in all Sacraments; even, in the Sacraments of the New Teſtament. There is one thing more yet to be obſerved, before we proceed to the next Part. In all the Ceremonies of the Law, Divines ſay, there are three things to be obſerved, that is,
<list>
                  <item>1. That they were Memorials of ſome Mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</item>
                  <item>2. That they were Types of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>3. That they did ſignifie ſome Moral Duty.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Whether all theſe things are to be ſound in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and how it was a Memorial of Mercy paſt, or how it was a Type of Chriſt, I will not now inquire, but pitch upon that which the Scripture ſhews to be undeniable, and that is this, That there was a Moral Duty ſignified by the Circumciſion; that there is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Circumciſion yet remaining, ſtill to be obſerved and practiſed by all the people of God, even now in the time of the Goſpel: And this is nothing elſe but the cutting off of carnal affections, the making of a new heart, and the putting off of the oldman. This is that the Apoſtle calls, <hi>Circumciſion made without hands, Col.</hi> 2.11. This is that the Apoſtle means, when he tells us, He <hi>is a Jew which is one inwardly, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98854:9"/>Circumciſion is that of the heart, Rom.</hi> 2.29. Nay, and even in the time of the Law, this was the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion that the Lord chiefly required, and therefore doth <hi>Moſes</hi> thus call upon the people, <hi>Circumciſe the foreskin of your heart, Deut.</hi> 10.16. And ſo doth the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> in the ſame words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. It doth not then a little concern us to conſider, whether we are thus ſpiritually circumciſed, yea or no. It was a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful threatning that was denounced againſt all thoſe of <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſterity, if they were not carnally circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, That <hi>Soul ſhall be cut off from his people, Gen.</hi> 17.14. And if the Spiritual Circumciſion, as hath been ſhewed, be more regarded by the Lord, ſhall not the neglect thereof be as ſeverely puniſhed as the neglect of the other? Surely the Prophet <hi>Jeremies</hi> words do make it good in that, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Circumciſe your ſelves to the Lord, and take away the foreskin of your hearts, ye men of Judah, and inhabitants of Jeruſalem, leſt my fury come forth like fire, and burn that none can quench it, becauſe of the evil of your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> Conſider then with thy ſelf, O Chriſtian, Haſt thou caſt off the works of Darkneſs? Doſt thou mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie thy Corruptions? Doſt thou deny Ungodlineſs and Worldly Luſts? If not, ſurely thou art not ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually circumciſed; but to uſe the Apoſtles phraſe, <hi>art dead in ſin, and the uncircumciſion of the fleſh, Col.</hi> 2.13. But to deſcend a little lower, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth intimate to us, That there is a Circumciſion of the Ear, and a Circumciſion of the Lips, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.10. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.30. Examine thy ſelf then, O Chriſtian, Doth thine Ear refuſe to hear the Voice of the Charmer? Or haſt thou an Itch in thine Ear to harken after novel Doctrines? Doth it delight to hear evil Reports, and to receive falſe Tales? And is it not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98854:10"/>then uncircumciſed? Doth thy tongue delight in ſcoffing, give it ſelf to ſwearing, whiſpering, or backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting? And is it not then uncircumciſed? Briefly, three things there were obſerved in the Circumciſion of the Fleſh, all which may ſerve to give us ſome further help and direction in this ſelf-examination.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Circumciſion could not be without dolour, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grief and pain. And certainly, foraſmuch as there is no man living that ſinneth not; nay, for as much as in many things we offend all, he who never felt any remorſe of Conſcience, that was never prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the heart whoſe heart, never ſmote him, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reckon himſelf ſpiritually circumciſed; and if it be but the corruption of our nature (and when Infants were circumciſed, they were guilty of no more), yet had we need with ſorrow of heart to humble our ſelves, and to cry out, <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death?</hi> To borrow the Apoſtles expreſſions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ancient Circumciſion did diſtinguiſh the <hi>Jews</hi> from other people. As the <hi>Grecians</hi> called all others <hi>Barbarians;</hi> ſo the <hi>Jews</hi> called all others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides themſelves, as it were by a reproachful and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious word, the Uncircumciſed, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.26. Yea, and they themſelves were by others reproached for their very Circumciſion. By the name of <hi>Judeus Apella,</hi> the Poet ſpeaks of him; So likewiſe, if we would be ſure that we are ſpiritually circumciſed, we muſt ſee there be a difference between us and worldly minded and voluptuous men that are in the world; not in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> thought well of themſelves and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed others, but in practice; for if there be as much vanity on thy back, as much venom in thy tongue, as much pride and malice in thy heart, as in the worſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98854:10"/>of men, never think thy ſelf to be ſpiritually cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed. <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe in their practiſe they differed not from <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Edom,</hi> from <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> are therefore ranked with them, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with them, as being uncircumciſed in heart, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.26.</p>
            <p>The third thing obſervable in the Circumciſion, was this; It was a Sacrament of Initiation, whereby they were as it were conſecrated unto God. They did thereby enter into Covenant with God, it was a ſign whereby they declared themſelves to be Gods peculiar people. And ſo ſurely, they that are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated unto God, and ſo live as perſons that are dedicated and conſecrated, can never reckon themſelves ſpiritually circumciſed; for the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We are the circumciſion, that ſerve God in the ſpirit;</hi> that is; in purity of life, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. He that is ſpiritually cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, and ſo devoted unto God, muſt yield no part of himſelf either of Body and Soul to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſervice then to the ſervice of God, <hi>ſite vovoris Deo, imitandus eſt tibi vitulus quem non licet hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manis operibus deſeruire, Origen. Hom.</hi> 14. <hi>in Num.</hi> A Bullock that is conſecrated unto God, it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to put it to any humane ſervice; and therein, ſaith he, muſt we be like him, if we have conſecrated our ſelves to God. But ah alas! how many be there, that ſo live as if they had bound themſelves by Indenture unto Satan, as if they had made themſelves by vow his Slaves, counting it there honour to be prophane, and their greateſt glory to ſtand at deſiance with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. Is it not a great abuſe for a conſecrated Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be turned into a Stable, or into a Sty to hold Swine in? But how much greater is the abuſe for the Body and Soul of a Chriſtian, conſecrated unto God, to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98854:11"/>become Satans work-houſe, for in ſuch <hi>Children of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience he worketh, Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. The ſum of all is, then Mortifie your members that are upon the Earth; if thy right hand offend thee, cut it off; cleanſe your ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit, for in this conſiſts the ſpiritual circumciſion (which neither is, nor ever will be abrogated) namely, in putting off the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the ſins of the fleſh, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. Ye ſee what this token of Gods love to <hi>Abraham</hi> was, both for the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the myſtery. In the letter it was in the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the foreskin of the fleſh. In the myſtery it was a ſign of the Covenant between God and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and withal did warn and admoniſh him to cut off all vile and carnal affections. This is the firſt thing obſervable in the Text. I ſhall firſt be briefer in the other parts that are behind. Come we then to the ſecond thing obſerved of what worth this token of love was, and that is imployed in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he gave,</hi> Saint <hi>Steven</hi> doth not ſay, he inflicted it as a puniſhment, or impoſed it as a burthen, he <hi>gave</hi> it as a token of love, out of his ſpecial faviour. Gods Ordinances are ſpecial bleſſings, of ſingular worth. The Almighty God promiſed to this man <hi>Abraham</hi> the whole Land of <hi>Canaan, Gen.</hi> 13, 14, 15. a bountiful gift; and yet this gift here ſpoken of, the Covenant of Circumciſion was of more worth then the whole Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> or all the Kingdoms of the world. It was a painful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but of ineſtimable worth, it was <hi>a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of faith. Rom.</hi> 4.11. and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it was a ſeal to aſſure him of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. All Gods ordinances are precious gifts, and that may appear firſt by the time which the Doner choſe for the beſtowing of them. When a man is parting from his friends, he will leave behind him ſome ſpecial
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98854:11"/>token of love and ſo the Apoſtle (ſaith when Chriſt Jeſus aſcended up on high he led Cativity Captive, and gave gifts to men, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8. and yet I confeſs the Apoſtle doth not allude ſo much to the parting of one friend from another) as to the cuſtome of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, who after their victories go up into their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in triumph carrying their captives bound, and then withal giving rich gifts to their friends; ſo Chriſt having conquered hell, and death, and ſin, and the Devil, led them captive and gave gifts unto men; but as to our purpoſe, the queſtion is, what thoſe gifts were, and the Apoſtle tell us, <hi>ibid. ver.</hi> 11. he <hi>gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. theſe are the chief gifts that Chriſt Jeſus thought good to give to his people (though the world doth not eſteem them ſo) even at the time of his triumph when he was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending into his greateſt glory, as if he had no greater gifts to beſtow upon them, and what is it for which they are reckoned by the Lord ſuch ſingular gifts, but only becauſe they are his meſſengers and the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of his holy word and ſacred ordinance? Theſe are gifts of high eſteem, and that doth thus appear, by the time when they were given, and that was at his aſcenſion; For as the coming of the Holy Ghoſt was a fruit of Chriſts aſcention; ſo alſo is the fitting of his meſſengers and the committing unto them the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of his ſacred ordinances, the fruit of the ſame aſcenſion. Secondly, the ſingular worth and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Gods ſacred ordinances doth appear in that, they to whom they are vouchſafed, are dignified by them. <hi>What nation is there ſo great,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> to the Iſrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, <hi>that hath ſtatutes and judgments ſo righteous as all this law which I ſet before you, Deut.</hi> 4.8. and it is worth your noteing, that whereas the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98854:12"/>was ſo highly dignified and commended; <hi>Dan</hi> 8.9. the pleaſant land; the glory of all lands, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.6. the land of deſire, <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.14. It was not for that there was ſuch plenty of ſilver and gold there for there was none at all, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.7, 8, 9. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſent to <hi>Ophir</hi> for Gold, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 9.28. and ſo did <hi>Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.48. but it was chiefly becauſe the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God were there ſetled. In reſpect here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is ſaid, that there <hi>the glory of God is ſeen in the ſanctuary, Pſal.</hi> 63.2. that is, at the Temple in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and his ſtatutes and ordinances he gave unto that people which was a mercy that he ſhewed not to any other nation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20. Thirdly, the worth and excellency of Gods ordinances do appear in the end and effect of them, for to this end they are given, and this is the effect of them, to beget grace in us and to bring us to Chriſt, ſuch is the excellency of the word of grace, that is of the Goſpel, that it is able to build us up and to give us an inheritance among them that are ſanctified, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.32. It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make us <hi>wiſe</hi> unto Salvation, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. and <hi>this wiſdom</hi> cannot be valued with the gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> gold and chriſtal cannot equal it, <hi>Job</hi> 28.16, 17. It was the myſtery of the Heathens, that they were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. and it is the moſt bleſſed and admirable uſe of the Sacraments to make us partakers of Chriſt. For as <hi>many of us as have been baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, have put, on Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 3.27. And the <hi>bread which we break</hi> (that is the other Sacrament) <hi>is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. ſuch is the worth thereof, it makes us partakers of Chriſt. All Gods ordinances are of eſtimable worth and excellency, and how comes it then to paſs that theſe ſhored ordinances are by ſo many ſlighted and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98854:12"/>neglected? The word by ſome, the ſacraments by others, both by moſt, and all the holy things of God, as if they were of no value. The things themſelves ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are heavenly bleſſings, but it is the wretchedneſs of thy heart, O man, and it is thy miſery thou doſt not know the worth of them; What is the reaſon the ſick man doth abhor all manner of meat; yea, the choiceſt dainties that can be provided? Is it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his body is poſſeſt with dangerous unwholſom malignant humours, which if not removed will inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably bring death? So when thou canſt not reliſh the food of thy Soul, what is the reaſon? Is it not becauſe thou art deſperately Soul-ſick? <hi>The natural man,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, (and certainly the natural man is deſperately Soul-ſick) <hi>he receiveth not the things of the ſpirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs unto him: Neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. And what will follow hereupon but inevitable deſtruction? The Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> was the Ordinance of God; The <hi>Phariſees</hi> refuſed to be baptized of him; What was the iſſue? They rejected the Councel of God againſt themſelves, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves, that is, to their own ruine, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.30. Shall the <hi>Manna</hi> be loathed, or any of Gods ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ordinances ſleighted? And ſhall not he be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Mark how he complains, <hi>I have written to him the great things of my Law, but they were counted as a ſtringe thing,</hi> Hoſ. 8.12. Neither will it be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to pretend the meanneſs either of the things of the Inſtitution, or of the Meſſengers that are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about them; It is a vain thing to ſay, can a little water on my Body waſh away the ſin of my Soul? Or can a bit of Bread, and ſip of Wine make me Partaker of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> No. It is not theſe things
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98854:13"/>that do the Work; But the Almighty God upon our right uſe of theſe things according to his appointment. He doth the Work, he cleanſeth us from our Sins, he makes us Partakers of his Son; It was not the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the of Rams Horns that threw down the Walls of <hi>Jericho,</hi> neither was it the Waters of <hi>Jordan</hi> that cured <hi>Naaman</hi> of his Leproſie, but the Almighty did both theſe Works upon the right uſing and obſerving what he had appointed. The like may be ſaid of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers by whom the Almighty doth ſend theſe Gifts, Are they mean in your ſight? Be it ſo, Yet will a man refuſe rich precious Treaſure, becauſe it is brought him in an Earthen Veſſel? We are Earthen Veſſels, but Treaſure we bring you. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. The Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> in the time of Famine, <hi>Had Bread and Fleſh brought to him in the Morning, and Bread and Fleſh in the Evening,</hi> the Ravens brought it to him by the Commandement of the Lord, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.4, 6. The Prophet knew very well that the Ravens were unclean Creatures, by the Lords own Verdict. <hi>Levit.</hi> 11.15. And yet he had more Wit and Grace then to refuſe that which they brought him from the Lord, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, beſides the Lords diſpleaſure, he might have periſhed for want of Food. I have but one thing more to add touching this point. Theſe Sacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which are of ſuch ineſtimable worth, the Lord hath vouchſafed to us in great meaſure, and all the days of our Lives we have injoyed them. Let us now bethink our ſelves of returning ſomthing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. The circumſtances of <hi>New years day</hi> are not yet quite over, Let us preſent the Lord with a <hi>New years Gift.</hi> Perhaps you will ſay, (and well ye may) <hi>What ſhall I return to the Lord for all his benefits? Pſ.</hi> 116.12. But is there nothing indeed? I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98854:13"/>a ſaying of <hi>Aeſchines</hi> a poor Diſciple of <hi>Socrates.</hi> Many brought to <hi>Socrates,</hi> many rich Gifts, poor <hi>Aeſchines</hi> had nothing, but he comes to <hi>Socrates,</hi> and ſaith unto him, <hi>Nihil dignum te quod dare tibi poſſim, invenio. Itaque dono tibi quod unum, habeo me ipſum;</hi> that is, I have nothing in the World wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be preſented to you, and therefore I beſtow upon you all that I have, my very Self; In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner let us give our Selves to God; So did they of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. And ſo doth the Apoſtle wiſh us all to do. <hi>I beſeech you brethren,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>by the mercies of God, that ye preſent your bodies a living ſacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, Rom.</hi> 12.1. and in the next verſe he ſhews how it is to be done, <hi>Be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind;</hi> So then, make you a new heart, let us begin to lead new lives, and this will be an acceptable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto God. For that is it, that God requires, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31. But the time bids me haſten to the third and fourth things, obſervable in the Text, that is, by <hi>whom,</hi> and <hi>to whom</hi> this Gift was given. I ſhall be brief in both. <hi>He</hi> gave <hi>Him. He,</hi> that is the God of Glory mentioned in verſe 2, <hi>He</hi> gave, and indeed Saint <hi>James</hi> tells us, that <hi>Every good gift, and every perfect gift is from above, and cometh down from the Father of Lights, Jam.</hi> 1.17. There is no mercy, no bleſſing that any man doth injoy, but it comes from him; What haſt thou, that thou haſt not received? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. Are they natural mercies? Why he <hi>giveth to all life and breath, Act.</hi> 17.25. Are they temporal bleſſings? Why, <hi>Both riches and honour come of thee,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.12. Are they ſpiritual bleſſings? <hi>If any of you lack wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98854:14"/>Jam.</hi> 1.5. Is it eternal happineſs it ſelf? Why, <hi>The giſt of God is eternal life, Rom.</hi> 6.23. Is it not ſtrange then, and may we not marvel at it, that God hath no more Friends? <hi>Every man,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, is a friend to him that giveth gifts, Pro.</hi> 19.6. And yet the Almighty God who giveth us all that we injoy, may ask the queſtion that <hi>Jehu</hi> once did, <hi>Who is on my ſide, who?</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.32. <hi>All ſeek their own, not the things which are Jeſus Chriſts,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle complains, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21. Every man is for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for his own profit, for his own pleaſure, for his own will. But you perhaps may ſay, who is not Gods Friend? For the anſwer of this, I ſhall but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Scripture or two unto you, as that in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.20. <hi>Thine enemies take thy name in vain.</hi> Why then common Swearers, and all others that any way abuſe the Name of God, are not his Friends; Again, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27, <hi>Thoſe mine enemies which would not that I ſhould raign over them, bring them hither and ſlay them before me,</hi> Why then, they that will not ſuffer the Lord to rule them and raign over them, are not his Friends. I will add but one more, and that in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 68.21. <hi>God ſhall wound the head of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the hairy ſcalp of ſuch a one as goeth on ſtill in his treſpaſſes.</hi> Why then, ſuch as go on ſtill in their treſpaſſes are not his Friends. Thoſe and many others may be declared to be ſuch as God doth not take for his Friends. And would we be his Friends indeed? Our Saviour ſhews us the way, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.14. <hi>Ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you.</hi> But this we ſhall touch again in the next point to which therefore I come and ſhall but briefly touch it.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt thing obſervable in the Text, is,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98854:14"/>to <hi>whom</hi> this token of Gods love was given. He gave <hi>Him,</hi> that is <hi>Abraham,</hi> as appears in the foregoing verſes of the Chapter, <hi>Abraham,</hi> as Saint <hi>James</hi> tells us, was called the <hi>friend</hi> of God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.23. two places there be in the Old Teſtiment, where <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> is called Gods <hi>Friend,</hi> that is, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 20.7. <hi>and Jſa.</hi> 41.8. To him was this Covenant of Circumciſion given, ſo Gods ſpecial gifts are for his <hi>ſpecial</hi> friends. The Preacher <hi>Eccles.</hi> 2.26. divides the world into two ſorts of people, and then he ſhews what gifts the Lord doth give to them both. <hi>God giveth to a man that is good in his ſight, wiſdom, and knowledg, and joy, but to the Sinner he giveth travel togather and to heap up,</hi> &amp;c. Wiſdom and knowledg in this world, and joy with the righteous in the world to come (as ſome expound the words) are Gods ſpecial gifts, and theſe he giveth not to all, but to the men that are <hi>good</hi> in his ſight, that is, ſuch as he accounts his <hi>friends.</hi> The <hi>favorites</hi> of an earthly Prince, as they do alwaies injoy more of the princes favour ſo do they alwaies partake more of his bounty, and the ſpecial tokens of his inward affections are vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed unto them, which are denied to others, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to thoſe that rebel againſt him: juſt ſo it is with the Almighty, and his friends or favorites. He give you but an inſtance or two. One is that of our Saviour to his diſciples whom he eſteemed his friends, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11. It is given unto you to know the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Kingdom of Heaven, but to them (that is to thoſe that are not his friends) it is not given. The other is that Prayer of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſa.</hi> 106.4. <hi>Remember me, O Lord, with the favour that thou beareſt unto thy people,</hi> he doth acknowledg there that God hath a ſpecial ſavour for ſome more then for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98854:15"/>others, and out of that favour he doth beſtow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them ſpecial gifts, health, and wealth, and riches, and honour, and the like he doth beſtow many times upon thoſe that are not his friends; but thoſe things that tend to the happineſs of the Soul, as wiſdom, and knowledg, and the Myſteries of the kingdom, and newneſs of heart, here ſignified by the Covenant of Circumciſion, theſe are Gods ſpecial bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and theſe, ye ſee, are only for his ſpecial friends. And if we would have them (and ſurely of all things in the world, they are moſt deſirable, as appears by that prayer of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> forementioned, <hi>Remember me, O Lord, with the favour that thou beareſt unto thy people</hi>) If I ſay; we would deſire to have them we muſt become his friends; be we therefore ſuch as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, and then we ſhall not miſs of them. Such as <hi>Abraham</hi> was? why, what a one was he? why, ſure in <hi>Abraham,</hi> if we would be like him, there are many things that we muſt take notice of.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In his carriage towards God.</item>
               <item>2. In his carriage towards his neighbours.</item>
               <item>3. In his carriage towards his own family.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. In his carriage towards God, we may obſerve that whereſoever he came he built an Altar, ſuch care he had of the Worſhip and Service of God, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.7, 8. and 13.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whatſoever God command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he was ready to obey, though it were never ſo againſt fleſh and blood: when he was called out of his Country from his kindred, and from his Fathers houſe, he obeyed and went forth, not knowing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he went, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8. when he was commanded to take his Son, his only Son, <hi>Iſaac</hi> whom he loved, and to offer him up for a burnt-offering, he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it without gain-ſaying, ſhewing thereby both
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98854:15"/>his readineſs to obey, and alſo to part with any thing, though never ſo dear unto him, for Gods ſake; he had faith and confidence in God, and doubted not of his promiſes even then, when unto human rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon there ſeemed little hope of them, as that he ſhould have a Son, when he was an hundred years old, and his Wife not onely ninety, but naturally barren, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18, 19, 20. And that in <hi>Iſaac</hi> his ſeed ſhould be called; and that all Nations ſhould be bleſſed in him, though he had a command to offer him up for a Burnt Offering, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his carriage towards his Neighbour, for there ye may ſee his Juſtice, his Mercy, and his Love of Peace, His Juſtice, in paying Tythes where they were due; <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> was the Prieſt of the moſt High God, and <hi>Abraham</hi> returning from the ſlaughter of the Kings, gave him the Tenth part of all, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.1, 2. His Mercy, in that he prayed to the Almighty God that he would be pleaſed to ſpare the Inhabitants of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> with the three other Cities of the Plain, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in that when they were oppreſſed and carried Captive, he armed his Trained Servants, and reſcued them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. And for his Love to Peace, when there was like to be a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between him and <hi>Lot,</hi> he was contented to part with his own right, rather than that there ſhould be any ſtrife between them; For though he were the elder man, and Lots Uncle, and though the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was given to him, and not to <hi>Lot,</hi> yet he gives <hi>Lot</hi> his choice, and wiſhes him to go into which part of the Land he pleaſed, that ſo there might be no danger of contention between them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In his carriage towards his own Family; for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98854:16"/>though <hi>Abraham</hi> were a great man, ſo great, that the Children of <hi>Heth</hi> ſaid unto him, <hi>Thou art a mighty Prince amongſt us, Gen.</hi> 23.5, 6. Yet he did not count it a work beneath himſelf, to have care of his Family, both Children and Servants, and to teach and inſtruct them in the ways of Piety and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>I know him,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>that he will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his Children and houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, Gen.</hi> 18.19. Theſe are the things that are eminent in <hi>Abraham,</hi> and in theſe things if we imitate him, as we ſhall be ſure by doing the works of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that we are the Children of <hi>Abraham, Joh.</hi> 8.39. So we may hope, God will reckon us his friends and take us into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with him, and be our God, as he was and is the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that he will beſtow upon us the choiceſt of his bleſſings, and bring us to ſit down at length with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Kingdom of Heaven. Which God of his mercy grant us, through the merits of his Son. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98854:16"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> ſince the dreadful Fire of <hi>London,</hi> to <hi>1676.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Guide to Eternity, by <hi>John Bona,</hi> uſeful for Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and fit to be given at Funerals.</item>
               <item>Dean <hi>W. Lloyd</hi>'s Sermon before the King, about Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>—His Sermon at the Funeral of <hi>John</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>—His Sermon before the King in Lent, 1673. 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>The Seaſonable Diſcourſe againſt Popery, in <hi>quarto.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>—The Defence of it, <hi>quarto.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>—The Difference betwixt the Church and Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>quarto.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>The Papiſts Apology to the Parliament anſwered. 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Naylor</hi>'s Commemoration Sermon for the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Col. <hi>Cavendiſh.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Sayers</hi> Sermon at the Aſſizes at <hi>Reading.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Tho. Tanner</hi>'s Sermon to the ſcattered Members of the Church. 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Stanhop</hi>'s four Sermons on ſeveral Occaſions, <hi>octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo,</hi> bound. 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Papal Tyranny,</hi> as it was exerciſed over <hi>England</hi> for ſome Ages, with two Sermons on the fifth of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Du Moulin,</hi> in <hi>quarto.</hi> 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>—His Sermon at the Funeral of Dr. <hi>Turner</hi> Dean of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> 6 <hi>d,</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Lany</hi>'s laſt Sermon, preached before the King, againſt Comprehenſion.</item>
               <item>Principals and Duties of Natural Religion. By <hi>John Wilkins,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr, <hi>Farindon</hi>'s 130 Sermons, in <hi>Folio,</hi> in three Vol.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Standiſh</hi>'s Sermon preached before the King, an <hi>White-Hall, September</hi> 26. 1675.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:98854:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
